A Guide to the Frederic G. Melcher-Robert Frost Collection,
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
- Series III: Miscellaneous Papers concerning Robert Frost
  - Program and Menu for "A Vermont Breakfast Party Commemorating the Fifth Award of the Limited Editions Club's Gold Medal," with a copy of a note from Robert Frost 1949 Nov 16 (Box-folder 3:28)
  - Program and Guest List for "The Poet and Reality A Conference in Honor of Robert Frost" 1950 Oct 6-8 (Box-folder 3:29)
  - Program, Guest List and Seating Arrangement for the Robert Frost Dinner, 1954 Mar 26 (Box-folder 3:30)
    The Lord Jeffery Inn, Amherst, Massachusetts.
  - Program for a Poetry Reading by Robert Frost at New York University 1956 Mar 23 (Box-folder 3:31)
  - Quotations by Robert Frost, 1916-1954, Typescript and Print (Box-folder 3:32)
  - Woodcut of Robert Frost by Bertrand Zadig [early 1920's] (Box-folder 3:33)
- Series IV: Miscellaneous Papers concerning Frederic G. Melcher and other Authors
  - The American Institute of Graphic Arts Membership Certificate issued to Frederic G. Melcher and other materials concerning the Institute and Melcher 1924, 1926, 1940 (Box-folder 3:34)
  - Article- Some Musical Analogies in Modern Poetry by Amy Lowell in The Musical Quarterly, n.d. (Box-folder 3:35)
  - Article- The Poetry Revival of 1914 by Edgar Lee Masters in The American Mercury, 1932 July, printed (Box-folder 3:36)
  - Article- The Fifty Books Idea by Frederic G. Melcher, 1936, offprint (Box-folder 3:37)
  - Article- Youth and Wings Edna St. Vincent Millay: Singer by Carl Van Doren, ca. 1924, reprint (Box-folder 3:38)
  - Article- Flame and Slag Carl Sandburg: Poet with Both Fists by Carl Van Doren in The Century Magazine, n.d., print (Box-folder 3:39)
  - Article- Shades and Shadows by Eleanor F. Wells in The English Journal, 1924 April, reprint (Box-folder 3:40)
  - Article- John Melcher[1850 Jun 15] (Box-folder 3:41)
    Typescript copy of an article from The Portsmouth Journal.
  - Articles by Frederic G. Melcher 1944-1958 (Box-folder 3:42)
  - Brochure concerning Camp Merryweather, Belgrade Great Pond, Maine, compliments of Laurie Richards 1905
  - Cartoon drawing of a cold day in London, 1923 May 31 (Box-folder 3:44)
  - Condolence letters concerning the death of Frederic G. Melcher 1963 (Box-folder 3:45)
  - Diary and Memoranda Book belonging to Frederic G. Melcher, 1896 (Box-folder 3:46)
    With an account dated March 31, 1918.
  - Drawings by Ernest Thompson Seton n.d. (Box-folder 3:47)
    Life Studies of Wild Squirrels inscribed by Seton to Frederic G. Melcher.
  - Driver's License belonging to Frederic G. Melcher from Great Britain 1936 (Box-folder 3:48)
  - Editorials by Frederic G. Melcher in The Publishers' Weekly, ca. 1937-1947, printed (Box-folder 4:1)
  - Essay- On Becoming Acquainted with Books by Frederic G. Melcher, 1962, printed (Box-folder 4:2)
  - Farewell Dinner for Frederic G. Melcher 1913 (Box-folder 4:3)
    Menu and Related Materials, leaving the employment of Charles E. Lauriat Company of Boston.
  - "A Greeting from B.L. Warde An American in England to Her Friends and Colleagues of the Printing Trade in America" addressed to Frederic G. Melcher, 1940 June, printed (Box-folder 4:4)
  - Invitation and Lists of Guests for a Dinner in Honor of James Whitcomb Riley, 1915 Oct 7 (Box-folder 4:5)
  - Invitation to meet the Queen of Romania from the North American Newspaper Alliance addressed to Mr. and Mrs. Frederic G. Melcher [1926] Oct 24 (Box-folder 4:6)
  - Miscellaneous Correspondence, ca. 1926-1962 (Box-folder 4:7)
    Chiefly appointments to positions on boards.
  - Miscellaneous Notes n.d. (Box-folder 4:8)
  - Miscellaneous Printed Ephemera 1923-1959, n.d. (Box-folder 4:9)
  - News clippings concerning Frederic G. Melcher and Daniel Melcher, etc. 1913-1963, n.d. (Box-folder 4:10)
  - Photograph of Daniel Melcher n.d. (Box-folder 4:11)
  - Photograph of Edna St. Vincent Millay n.d. (Box-folder 4:12)
  - Photographs and Postcards concerning the Melchers ca. 1913-1959 (Box-folder 4:13)
  - Place cards from a lunch at the White House on the occasion of the presentation of books to the White House Library 1933 (Box-folder 4:14)
  - Poem- Broadway's Canyon by John Gould Fletcher, n.d., printed (Box-folder 4:15)
  - Poem- Winter's Turning by Amy Lowell, n.d., printed (Box-folder 4:16)
  - Poem- Cool Tombs by Carl Sandburg, n.d. (Box-folder 4:17)
  - Poem- The Laughters by Louis Untermeyer, n.d., printed (Box-folder 4:18)
  - Press Release concerning annual meeting of the American Country Life Association 1939 (Box-folder 4:19)
  - Programs and Invitations ca. 1930-1940 (Box-folder 4:20)
- Series V: Correspondence of Frederic G. Melcher with Various Authors and Publishers
  - Miscellaneous Cut Autographs, including Irving Bacheller, W.H. Crane, Harry Davenport, Louis Charles Elson, William Mahone, Thomas Nelson Page, James Whitcomb Riley, and Daniel Webster 1865, 1894-1899, n.d. (Box-folder 4:21)
  - George Ade explains that he does all of his writing in pencil and not on a typewriter 1932 May 31 (Box-folder 4:22)
  - Elmer Adler asks Melcher to visit him in Princeton and thanks him for becoming a member of Amigos de Calle del Cristo in San Juan, Puerto Rico, and helping the collection grow. 1940, 1959 (Box-folder 4:23)
  - American Antiquarian Society, Director Clarence S. Bingham, asks Melcher to speak 1956 Jan 18, 19 (Box-folder 4:24)
  - American Institute of Graphic Arts notifies Melcher that he is the recipient of the Institute Medal 1945 Apr 14, 17 (Box-folder 4:25)
  - American Library Association, President Charles H. Compton, 1935, 1960, Answers Melcher's required reading for the New Year question (1935) and thanks him for his contribution to the building fund (1960). (Box-folder 4:26)
  - Joe Anthony, Newark Evening News, 1919 Apr 17 (Box-folder 4:27)
    Mentions the League of Nations stories and an editorial about them that he was asked to write.
  - Sir Edwin Arnold (1832-1904) [1901] Dec 5 (Box-folder 4:28)
    Says he cannot identify the poem they are seeking but thinks their client may be interested in one of his two books, Indian Idylls and Lotus and Jewel.
  - Joseph Auslander, 1942 May, Asks Melcher to consider the Library of Congress as a repository for his collection of Fine Printing and Bibliography. (Box-folder 4:29)
  - Mary Austen discusses her article for Publishers' Weekly, 1920-1921 (Box-folder 4:30)
  - Edgar J. Banks sends Melcher a genuine ancient Babylonian tablet from Drehem, a suburb of Nippur, with a detailed description of its inscription. 1923 Apr 2 (Box-folder 4:31)
  - James Barnes refers to his visit to the Nassau Club to speak on copyright and censorship. 1930 Apr 12 (Box-folder 4:32)
  - Bernard M. Baruch answers Melcher's question concerning required reading for the New Year 1935 Jan 7 (Box-folder 4:33)
  - [Edwin De Turck Bechtel] describes a recent talk by Robert Frost interspersed with his poems, n.y. Nov 16 (Box-folder 4:34)
    During the talk Frost spoke of his dear friends who have meant so much to him in the writing and publishing of his poems, mentioning Melcher prominently as one who was "a perfect guide and intermediary between himself and publishers, printers, bibliophiles and such."
  - William Rose Benet mentions the book on General Booth, 1920, 1929, William Rose Benet mentions the book on General Booth that he has to review for The New York Evening Post (1920) and a notice he wants placed in Publishers' Weekly warning people about a "certain abominable hack writer whose acquaintance with my wife was very slight" who has claimed he was commissioned to prepare her biography (1929). (Box-folder 4:35)
  - Ralph Bergengren thanks Melcher for his mention of Jane, Joseph, and John in Herald Tribune Books1936 Nov 15 (Box-folder 4:36)
  - Albert J. Beveridge congratulates Melcher on becoming the editor at Publisher's Weekly and writes that he will be greatly missed by himself, the store, and the community of Indianapolis. 1918 May 10 (Box-folder 4:37)
  - Joseph Blumenthal invites the Melchers to visit, n.d., Joseph Blumenthal invites the Melchers to visit just following the talk of Robert Frost at the New School on April 7th. (Box-folder 4:38)
  - Eugene Boissevain arranges a date and fee for his wife, Edna St. Vincent Millay, to speak at Montclair, New Jersey. 1924 Dec-1925 (Box-folder 4:39)
  - Boy Scouts of America invites Melcher to a luncheon, 1924, 1943 (Box-folder 4:40)
    Boy Scouts of America invites Melcher to a luncheon with Douglas Fairbanks (1924) and sends to Melcher a Boy Scout lapel button and certificate (not present) as member of the National Council (1943)
  - James Boyd recommends Melcher get Herschel Brickell in New York to do the job he has in mind because his own familiarity with Southern Literature is very uneven and has many gaps. 1935 Mar 23 (Box-folder 4:41)
  - William Stanley Braithwaite sends Melcher a set of advance sheets, 1912-1913, 1962 (Box-folder 4:42)
    William Stanley Braithwaite sends Melcher a set of advance sheets for his anthology of magazine verse for 1913. Also present is a note from Melcher to Braithwaite about his account (1912), an obituary and notice of his funeral services (1962).
  - Anna Hempstead Branch accepts the invitation to Robert Frost's birthday party and sends her three dollars. 1925 Mar 9 (Box-folder 4:43)
  - John Buchan (Lord Tweedsmuir) gives Melcher permission to quote from his letter, 1928 Apr 10, n.y. Jan 11 (Box-folder 4:44)
    John Buchan (Lord Tweedsmuir) gives Melcher permission to quote from his letter about Mr. Paine's Booklovers Map of the British Isles (1928) and thanks him for his kindness and introduction at the gathering, which he enjoyed very much (Jan 11).
  - Pearl S. Buck discusses his invitation (1935), 1935-1951 (Box-folder 4:45)
    Pearl S. Buck discusses his invitation (1935); her desire for Melcher to serve on the board of judges who select the monthly book used in the forums for librarians for The East and West Association (1943); his willingness to serve on the Board of Directors of The East and West Association (1948); the suspension of the publication of the magazine People (1949); and the announcement that she is suspending the activities of The East and West Association (1951) due to financial considerations.
  - Gelett Burgess thanks Melcher for his talk, 1921, 1926 (Box-folder 4:46)
    Gelett Burgess thanks Melcher for his talk and asks if he knows any really good traveling salesmen who know how books are sold on the road (1921); and asks for three copies of The Publisher's Weekly for Nov 6th or 7th, which contains a bibliography of his works (1926).
  - Ellis Parker Butler recommends Irving Stone's novel, n.d. (Box-folder 4:47)
    Ellis Parker Butler recommends Irving Stone's novel about Vincent Van Gogh, Lust For Life, deeming it "the most intensely interesting book I have read in year..." and "inevitably destined to become a classic of fictional biography."
  - Witter Bynner regrets that he is unable to attend Robert Frost's dinner (1925), 1925-1926, n.d. (Box-folder 4:48)
    Witter Bynner regrets that he is unable to attend Robert Frost's dinner (1925); sends corrections for the page of his first editions as it appears in Publisher's Weekly before it appears in book form (1926); and a short humorous verse (n.d.) concerning Robert Frost: "I have a Boy's Will North of Bosting A New Hampshire Cake With Robert Frosting"
  - James Branch Cabell thanks Mr. Nicholson for his gracious appreciation of his book and for recommending it to a bookseller, 1917, 1934 (Box-folder 4:49)
    He reveals that "America has simply not produced an adequate literature anywhere." (1917); finds that he is unable to write an article on Guy Holt for Melcher, as he is still deeply affected by his death (1934).
  - Marion G. Canby thanks Melcher for his sincere and comforting letter of sympathy following the death of her husband, Henry Seidel Canby (1878-1961), 1961 May 24 (Box-folder 4:50)
  - Carl Carmer, President of The P.E.N., A World Association of Writers, expressing his delight that Melcher has become a Vice-President of the P.E.N, 1943 May 6 (Box-folder 4:51)
  - Willa Cather is grateful that Melcher likes her book, [One of Ours?] (1922), 1922, 1926, n.d. (Box-folder 4:52)
    Regrets that she does not have time to do a talk for him (1926); says of Jurgen, "I've had the greatest fun with Jurgen! If the indecent parts of the book were cut out, there is [?] nothing interesting left, but that's a real merit. In most American books the indecency is so unessential, even when its put there with a swagger." She also assures him that "you are the only man connected with the selling end of the book trade whom it doesn't make me vastly blue to talk with." (n.d.); Also present are two undated calling cards from Cather telling when she will be at home at Five Bank Street.
  - Mary Ellen Chase thanks Melcher for the August article about her in Publisher's Weekly, [1934?] Sep, n.d. (Box-folder 4:53)
    Mary Ellen Chase thanks Melcher for the August article about her in Publisher's Weekly and informs him that she will be sailing for England on the 8th or 9th of September when her book, Mary Peters, is released. She also thanks him for his kind letter about the book that she read on the train to New York.
  - Thomas Maitland Cleland, American book and type designer, expresses his gratitude for Melcher's assessment of his career and his show at the Century. 1959 Aug 12 (Box-folder 4:54)
  - Elizabeth Coatsworth expresses her thanks for a radio gift in a flippant rhyme complete with oblique references to her book, The Cat Who Went to Heaven, 1931 July 4 (Box-folder 4:55)
  - Melcher writes to bookseller Louis Henry Cohn, 1944 Mar 23 (Box-folder 4:56)
    Melcher writes to bookseller Louis Henry Cohn, relaying what Robert Frost had to say about autographed poems in Frost editions which he had done for E. Ording on request and his suspicion that Conti was H. Knauti. (See also Frost letters, 1944).
  - Timothy Cole writes that he will be present at the Art Center to receive the great honor bestowed by the directors of the Graphic Arts, 1927 Oct 15 (Box-folder 4:57)
  - Padraic Colum is unable to attend the banquet in honor of Robert Frost due to a prior engagement. n.d. (Box-folder 4:58)
  - Dr. James B. Conant, Harvard University, asks Melcher to serve on a special committee, 1945 Nov 6, 9 (Box-folder 4:59)
    Dr. James B. Conant, Harvard University, asks Melcher to serve on a special committee to hire a successor for the Director of the Harvard University Press, Mr. Scaife, and Melcher accepts.
  - Grace Hazard Conkling, Hampshire Bookshop, Inc. accepts his invitation to the Robert Frost dinner (1925), 1925-1926 (Box-folder 4:60)
    Grace Hazard Conkling, Hampshire Bookshop, Inc. accepts his invitation to the Robert Frost dinner (1925); and agrees to speak at Montclair, New Jersey, with Melcher's reply (1926).
  - Malcolm Cowley asks Melcher to write a short review about the White Oak Library and thanks him for doing so. 1934 Mar 22, Apr 5 (Box-folder 4:61)
    Malcolm Cowley asks Melcher to write a short review about the White Oak Library and thanks him for doing so.
  - Wilbur L. Cross, Editor of The Yale Review, accepts his invitation to the Robert Frost dinner, 1925 Feb 28 (Box-folder 4:62)
  - Countee Cullen regrets that his teaching duties prevents him from attending Melcher's convention at Lake Mohonk on September 28th. 1934 Sep 4 (Box-folder 4:63)
  - James Henry Daugherty mentions Daniel Boone and the last Horn Book, 1940 Jul 22 (Box-folder 4:64)
    James Henry Daugherty mentions Daniel Boone and the last Horn Book as examples of his good work and proclaims, "I do so now [acknowledge Melcher] happy to know that all good books as well as children's books have so active a champion and so articulate and creative an imagination to speak and strike in their cause."
  - Elmer Davis thanks Melcher for the book containing his remarks and Melcher's introduction (1946), 1946, 1954 (Box-folder 4:65)
    Discusses the testimony of Mr. Gaines and danger of censorship and his gratitude for listing him first in non-fiction in the Publisher's Weekly (1954).
  - John Doan supplies his suggestion for "required reading" requested by Melcher, as Walter Pach's Ananias or the False Artist. 1934 Dec 29 (Box-folder 4:66)
  - Edward H. Dodd, Jr. sends an advance copy of Winston Churchill's Birth of Britain to Melcher, 1956 Mar 1, 9 (Box-folder 4:67)
    Edward H. Dodd, Jr. sends an advance copy of Winston Churchill's Birth of Britain to Melcher, and calls bringing it into print an exhilarating and inspiring experience. Also mentions that Churchill had finished Volume II and was working on Volume III.
  - Marion Dodd, The Hamphire Bookshop, Inc., mentions that she has recently purchased from Robert Frost a number of his poems, 1930 Feb 1, 3 (Box-folder 4:68)
    Marion Dodd, The Hamphire Bookshop, Inc., mentions that she has recently purchased from Robert Frost a number of his poems, two original drafts, and a copybook containing the poem "New Hampshire." She asks Melcher what she should pay for them, but Melcher declines to value the manuscripts and suggests she check American Book Prices Current.
  - George H. Doran thanks Melcher for how he used his article on Hester Hunter, 1935 Oct 22 (Box-folder 4:69)
    George H. Doran thanks Melcher for how he used his article on Hester Hunter and hopes it encourages "talented and energetic women to open bookshops in their homes." He also asks to borrow the two half-tones used in the article.
  - John Dos Passos writes that he enjoyed their lunch, 1949 Aug 9 (Box-folder 4:70)
    John Dos Passos writes that he enjoyed their lunch and that there appeared to be a small break on passage costs for P.E.N. members. He also asks if John Marquand was going [on the voyage] ?
  - Frank Nelson Doubleday (1862-1934) offers to arrange a tour for him at their Kingswood plant while he is in London attending book meetings. 1931 May 1 (Box-folder 4:71)
  - Lloyd C. Douglas accepts an invitation to dinner at Melcher's home, 1943-1944 (Box-folder 4:72)
    Lloyd C. Douglas accepts an invitation to dinner at Melcher's home which he thoroughly enjoyed (1943) and sends an article for the forthcoming religious number of Publisher's Weekly requested by Melcher (1944).
  - Theodore Dreiser discusses in detail the facts that he feels that each publisher should take into account with their affidavits concerning his arbitration case with the Liveright Publishing Corporation over the cost of the plates of his work and the price per copy of his bound books (April 30, 1934), 1934-1935 (Box-folder 4:73)
    Theodore Dreiser discusses in detail the facts that he feels that each publisher should take into account with their affidavits concerning his arbitration case with the Liveright Publishing Corporation over the cost of the plates of his work and the price per copy of his bound books (April 30, 1934). He also thanks Melcher very much for his assistance in submitting an affidavit to the arbitration on his behalf (May 10, 1934). In answer to Melcher's request for his suggestion for "required reading," Dreiser declines as there are too many from which to choose.
  - Will Durant, takes a moment from his own work T he Story of Civilization to give his recommendations for required reading, 1934 Dec 29 (Box-folder 4:74)
    Will Durant, takes a moment from his own work The Story of Civilization to give his recommendations for required reading, "I should recommend to the reader who wishes to be profoundly instructed and moved, Dostoievski's novel The Brothers Karamazov; and to the reader who is tough-minded enough to care for instruction without amusement, Spengler's Decline of the West. I think the novels of Pearl Buck show a fine understanding of human life. William Henry Chamberlain's Russia's Iron Age seems to be the best recent survey of the Communist experiment in Russia. Or let the reader digest the book of Ecclesiastes, and tell me how God ever let that dour tract into the Bible."
  - W.A. Dwiggins asks for a copy of the article in Publisher's Weekly about his work (1928), 1928, 1939 (Box-folder 4:75)
    W.A. Dwiggins asks for a copy of the article in Publisher's Weekly about his work (1928); and shares his thoughts about a Twenty Years After article for the Publisher's Weekly (1939).
  - Walter Prichard Eaton discusses his article on fine printing for The Bookman (1921), 1921-1935 (Box-folder 5:1)
    Suggests that the topic of his lecture at Montclair, New Jersey, will be a talk on the amateur revival in our theater and its meaning for American life (December 28, 1924 & January 2, 1925); accepts invitation to the Frost dinner and asks about a manuscript for twenty-five one-act plays (March 3, 1925); arranges to stay with Melcher during a lecture at Monclair, New Jersey, but says that his wife never attends his lectures, "She stays home and reads Edgar Wallace" (1932); discusses the play Uncle Tom and its possibilities (June 3, 1933); sends a brief review of February Hill by Victoria Lincoln, "Drama, humor and beauty in a sordid shack & sordid lives in -of all places!- Fall River" (January 5, 1935); and writes briefly about his motor trip in Great Britain (September 2, 1935).
  - Walter D. Edmonds graciously refuses an invitation to speak before the Library Association's Convention, 1936 Jul 28 (Box-folder 5:2)
  - T.S. Eliot agrees to attend a reception given by the English Speaking Union and the East West Association on December 4th for him while he is in New York on other business. 1950 Oct 12, 16 (Box-folder 5:3)
  - John Erskine thanks Melcher for his kind introduction during his address in Montclair, New Jersey (1922); and accepts an invitation to the Robert Frost dinner (1925). 1922, 1925 (Box-folder 5:4)
  - Luther H. Evans, Librarian of Congress, regrets that Melcher was unable to attend the Dec 12th event, 1951 Jan 10 (Box-folder 5:5)
  - Geoffrey Faber sends a letter in lieu of a Christmas card which are practically taboo in Great Britain during the war. 1943 Dec 7 (Box-folder 5:6)
  - Rachel Field shares her excitement and pleasure at winning the Newbery Medal, for Hitty: Her First Hundred Years 1930-1931, 1936 (Box-folder 5:7)
    Rachel Field shares her excitement and pleasure at winning the Newbery Medal, for Hitty: Her First Hundred Years and her presence at the California American Library Association meeting and thanks Melcher for all the good publicity she received from Publisher's Weekly (July 19, 1930); thanks him for sending Esther Burr (1931) and responding quickly about Wilson Follett (1936).
  - [Edward A. Filene], Wm. Filene's Sons Company, recommends The Autobiography of Lincoln Steffens saying that "Steffens is the wisest man I know in his judgment of men and events in this country." 1935 Jan 2 (Box-folder 5:8)
  - Dr. Morris Fishbein, editor of The Journal of the American Medical Association, recommends The Forty Days of Musa Dagh by Franz Werfel because of its emphasis on the rights of minorities. 1935 Jan 7 (Box-folder 5:9)
  - Dorothy Canfield Fisher regrets that she is unable to accept speaking engagements while her children are still young, 1924-1956, n.d. (Box-folder 5:10)